{"tossups": [{"question": "The event for which this man is most remembered for occurred on March 2, 1962. During that game, the Knicks deliberately fouled other players to keep the ball away from this man, who at the time played for the Philadelphia Warriors. For 10 points, name this man who holds the NBA record for most points in a regular season with 4,029, and who was the first and only NBA player to score 100 points in a game.", "answer": "Wilt <b><u>Chamberlain</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "With Douglas Fairbanks, Mary Pickford, and Charlie Chaplin, this man co-founded United Artists. A film by this director was the first film to be shown privately at the White House and was praised by Woodrow Wilson. That film by this director was criticized for its positive portrayal of the Ku Klux Klan. For 10 points, name this director of <em>Birth of a Nation</em>.", "answer": "D.W. <b><u>Griffith</u></b> [David Llewelyn Wark <b><u>Griffith</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "After a 1515 French victory outside this city, the Swiss Confederacy swore an eternal truce with the French. This site of the Battle of Marignano was ruled by Ludovico il Moro, who commissioned Leonardo\u2019s <em>The Last Supper</em>. Until falling under French and Spanish control, this city was ruled by the Sforza family. For 10 points, name this Northern Italian city.", "answer": "<b><u>Milan</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man shocked both Catholic and Protestant countries when he ordered the burning of Michael Servetus. This man, who explained his religious views in the book <em>Institutes of the</em> <em>Christian Religion</em>\u00b8 advocated the \"TULIP\" philosophy as the civil authority in Geneva. For 10 points, name this founder of a strict, predestination-focused Protestant theology.", "answer": "John <b><u>Calvin</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "This man rose to the head of his party after he was targeted by the Zhongshan Warship Incident. This man and his wife propounded the semi-fascist New Life Movement, and he was the first commandant of the Whampoa Military Academy. His wife Soong May-ling supposedly had an affair with Wendell Wilkie, and he succeeded Sun Yat-Sen as leader of the KMT. For 10, points, name this longtime president of Taiwan and nationalist leader during the Chinese Civil War.", "answer": "<b><u>Chiang</u></b> Kai-Shek", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man coined the term \"timocracy\" for a government by property-owners, which he deemed the second-best of five possible governments. He used the parable of the divided line to explain the process of understanding and analogized the visible world as shadows on the wall of a cave. For 10 points, name this Greek who advocated \"philosopher-kings\" in <em>The Republic</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Plato</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This man's memoir noted that the FBI sent agents to take notes on his bar mitzvah in an attempt to prove his parents' Communist Party membership, which he admitted. This man wrote <em>His Holiness</em>, a biography of Pope John Paul II, and the Hillary Clinton bio <em>A Woman in Charge</em>. For 10 points, name this reporter who broke the Watergate story with Bob Woodward.", "answer": "Carl <b><u>Bernstein</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This text is the subject of the Supreme Court case <em>Minersville v. Gobitis</em>. This text was originally recited while saluting outward, a recommendation changed after World War II. Michael Newdow filed several lawsuits attempting to remove a phrase added in the 1950s, \"under God,\" from this text. For 10 points, name this Francis Bellamy-written ode to the U.S. flag.", "answer": "<b><u>Pledge of Allegiance</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This type of song was repopularized by the Fisk Jubilee Singers. A song of this type written by Charles Wesley says \"My brother, you ought to been there;\" another of these songs repeats \"Tell old Pharaoh, let my people go.\" For 10 points, \"Roll, Jordan, Roll\" and \"Go Down Moses\" are examples of what kind of Christian song often sung by slaves in the antebellum South?", "answer": "<b><u>spiritual</u></b>s  <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 3 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Jazz"}, {"question": "This author lived among the East End poor for six months to write <em>The People of the Abyss</em>, advocated for the genocide of China in \"The Unparalleled Invasion,\" and described a dystopian U.S. in <em>The Iron Heel</em>. For 10 points, name this American author who chronicled Yukon gold rushers in \"To Build a Fire\" and a novel about the dog Buck, <em>The Call of the Wild</em>.", "answer": "Jack <b><u>London</u></b> [Jack John Griffith <b><u>London</u></b>]", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "This woman was travelling with Laura Havilland when she was bruised by a streetcar conductor, leading to the desegration of public transit in Washington, D.C. Earlier, this woman said she wanted to \"fill her pint of intellect\" in a speech in Akron. For 10 points, name this former slave who advocated for abolition and women's equality in the \"Ain't I A Woman\" speech.", "answer": "Sojourner <b><u>Truth</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Bernard de Launay was killed during this event. It was lead by Pierre-Augustin Hulin, and partially sparked by the dismissal of the finance minister Jacques Necker three days before. Celebrated on a holiday observed on July 14, this event liberated a mere seven prisoners. For 10 points, name this 1789 event in which an angry mob sacked a Parisian prison.", "answer": "storming of the <b><u>Bastille</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "French citizens accused of this activity were often charged with \u201cstate of indignity.\u201d Jozef Tiso was convicted and hanged for this crime in Czechoslovakia. The \u00c9puration was a series of trials in France for this crime, of which Philippe P\u00e9tain and other leaders in the Vichy government were found guilty. For 10 points, name this crime of assisting an occupying army.", "answer": "Nazi <b><u>collaboration</u></b> [or Axis <b><u>collaboration</u></b>; or German <b><u>collaboration</u></b>; prompt on \u201ctreason\u201d]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "William Christopher replaced George Morgan on this show as chaplain Mulcahy. This show had two spinoffs, including the contemporary-set <em>Trapper John, M.D.</em> This TV show was based on a 1970 Robert Altman film, and its 1983 finale remains the highest-rated episode of a scripted TV show ever. For 10 points, name this sitcom set during the Korean War.", "answer": "<em><b><u>M*A*S*H</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "A park in an old capital of this nation kept a herd of inviolable sacred deer. Cord-marked pottery was a hallmark of its Stone Age Jomon culture. This modern-day country made tombs called <em>kofun</em> during an era when it began importing Chinese culture and received Buddhist envoys from Korea. For 10 points, name this Asian nation whose Yamato clan ruled it from Nara prefecture.", "answer": "<b><u>Japan</u></b> [or <b><u>Nihon</u></b>; or <b><u>Nippon</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Subgroups called <em>iwi</em> divided these people, who argued based on language differences that they never meant to cede sovereignty to William Hobson in the 1840 Treaty of Waitangi. Hone Heke was a chief of these people. Some of their men mark themselves with swirling lines of <em>ta</em> <em>moko,</em> a type of carved-in ink tattoo. For 10 points, name these indigenous inhabitants of New Zealand.", "answer": "<b><u>Ma\u014dri</u> </b>people [or <b><u>tangata whenua</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The \"flag-follower\" expeditions of miners departed from this city in the eighteenth century. The painting <em>Independence or Death</em> depicts events that took place in this city, which are also remembered at the Ipiranga (<b>ee-pee-RON-guh</b>) Monument. For 10 points, name this city where Pedro I declared the independence of Brazil, which is now the country's most populous.", "answer": "<b><u>S\u00e3o Paulo</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's treatise</u> </b><em><b><u>Mechanics</u> </b></em><b><u>advanced the notion that inertia is derived from the mass</u></b> <b><u>of every other body in the universe, now known as his \"principle.\" His</u> </b><em><b><u>History of</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Mechanics</u> </b></em><b><u>introduced to Einstein the idea of non-absolute space. This German (+)</u></b> <b>philosopher of science who also discovered shock waves produced when the (*)</b> speed of sound is exceeded. For 10 points, identify this man who thus lends his name to a \"number\" denoting the proportion to the speed of sound.", "answer": "Ernst <b><u>Mach</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "<b><u>After this war, the</u> </b><em><b><u>Titulus Regius</u></b></em><b><u> was repealed. During this war, a king negotiated the</u></b> <b><u>Treaty of Piquniny with \u201cthe Universal Spider,\u201d Louis XI. A leader of one of this war\u2019s</u></b> <b><u>sides married Elizabeth (+)</u> Woodville, thus alienating his ally Warwick the Kingmaker. This war ended after (*)</b> Richard III was defeated at the Battle of Bosworth Field. For 10 points, name this conflict between the houses of Lancaster and York, which were represented by red and white flowers.", "answer": "War of the <b><u>Roses</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In response to this event, a system was announced in which alternate-day accessibility</u></b> <b><u>was determined by the last digit of a car's license plate. This event, a classic example of an</u></b> <b><u>economic (+)</u> \"supply shock,\" was a response to perceived U.S. support of Israel in the Yom Kippur War. This event was engineered by (*)</b> OPEC and devastated the economy under Richard Nixon. For 10 points, identify this 1973 event which caused long lines at gas stations.", "answer": "OPEC <b><u>oil embargo</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Judica-Cordiglia recordings purportedly captured transmissions from the \"lost\"</u></b> <b><u>group of these people, whose existence or death is believed to have been suppressed. One of</u></b> <b><u>these people died in a 1968 (+) fighter jet crash, seven years after using the Vostok. These</u></b> <b><u>people included (*)</u></b> Valentina Tereshkova and Yuri Gagarin. For 10 points, identify these people who included the first-ever man in space, and were the stars of the Soviet space program.", "answer": "<b><u>cosmonaut</u></b>s [prompt on descriptive answers]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In retirement from politics, this man wrote a bizarre novel about a conspiracy to destroy</u></b> <b><u>the United States, entitled</u> </b><em><b><u>The Canfield Decision</u></b></em><b><u>. This man was mocked as receiving \"the</u></b> <b><u>greatest deal since the Lord spared Isaac on the mountaintop\" when he was able to plead</u></b> <b><u>to only</u> (+) tax evasion after accepting substantial bribes, causinghis 1973</b> (*) resignation. For 10 points, name this Greek-American, and Maryland-born Vice-President under Richard Nixon.", "answer": "Spiro <b><u>Agnew</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Police in this city fought with demonstrators at Admiralty, Causeway Bay, and Mong</u></b> <b><u>Kok during protests that were centered at the Connaught and Harcourt Road area. Those</u></b> <b><u>protests in this city, grew out of the</u> (+) Occupy Central movement founded by Joshua Wong and Lester Shum. (*)</b> For 10 points, name this city where the \"Umbrella Revolution\" movement seeks to accelerate democratization following a 2014 decision on electoral reforms from China, which has governed this city since 1997.", "answer": "<b><u>Hong Kong</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's security forces were denounced as \"doberman thugs\" by the U.S.</u></b> <b><u>President after attacking Billy Ford. This home of the Dignity Battalions was where the</u></b> <b><u>Vatican embassy was targeted by loud (+)</u> rock music in Operation Nifty Package. The U.S. signed the Carter-Torrjos Treaty with this country, which was invaded in Operation (*) </b>Just Cause. For 10 points, name this country where Manuel Noriega was displaced from overseeing a canal.", "answer": "<b><u>Panama</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the 1920s, this party divided into \"black and tan\" and \"lily white\" factions in a</u></b> <b><u>dispute over allowing African-American support. A dissident faction of this party briefly</u></b> <b><u>broke away in 1870 under Carl Schurz and cross-nominated (+)</u> Horace Greeley for President in 1872; that party appended the word (*)</b> \"liberal\" to this party's name. For 10 points, name this party that engineered Reconstruction, and won the Presidency under Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "<b><u>Republican</u></b> Party [or <b><u>G.O.P.</u></b>; or <b><u>Grand Old Party</u></b>]  <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 3 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras \u2013 ONLY READ IF YOU NEED A BACKUP OR TIEBREAKER! </b> <b><u>This battle marked the end of a man who had earlier survived a duel with Felix Huston.</u></b>  <b><u>Everett Peabody accidentally started this battle ahead of schedule. The Fallen Timbers</u></b> <b><u>charge at this battle was led by (+)</u> Nathan Bedford Forrest, and Lew Wallace missed most of this battle after getting lost. This battle included the charge on the (*)</b> \"Hornet\u2019s Nest\" and the death of Albert Sidney Johnston. For 10 points, name this 1862 Civil War battle in  Tennessee.  ANSWER: Battle of <b><u>Shiloh</u></b> [or Battle of <b><u>Pittsburg Landing</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}